So there's a lot of things that can make
of course our our what digital
missionaries or Catholic creators are
doing easier. But thing is there's a lot
of content that's being pred produced
that's mass-produced that's no quality
not attractive and yes a lot of
devotional content that's out there that
says things that saints said that's not
true or have other things which are good
things at the end good messages go to
mass etc there's a lot of deep fakes
right now of the pope a lot of deep
fakes from from that are inviting to do
good things and we have to be wary of
those things and also put a line cuz
even though they're inviting us to the
sacraments to do good things and they're
orthodox let's say
>> it's not the pope
[Music]
>> Jose Diti it's fantastic to have this
opportunity to be with you this morning
um so what we want to touch on since we
have limited time here is um the Juan
Diego Network the people that you work
with you guys know uh influencers, you
know the social media landscape better
than anyone in the world. Um with AI,
with emerging tech, what are some of the
opportunities that you that you see
ahead that uh that can really help with
evangelization that can really help and
have a positive impact on people's
spiritual lives, but also what are some
of the challenges? I know early on we
were talking a little bit about deep
fakes. Um there's a lot of things that
are happening.
I don't know if 25 minutes will will cut
it or half an hour, but so many things
to talk about AI that the challenges
well I think are are very evident but
let's try to start with with the the
cool things of evangelization. It helps
us and let's say Catholic creators in a
lot of ways to do our our job faster,
right? like the research which we have
to verify or choose good sources like
magisterium etc right because if not so
many things like chip still thinks pope
Francis is a pope right if you don't ask
directly so there's a lot of things that
can make of course our are what digital
missionaries or Catholic creators are
doing easier but thing is there's a lot
of content that's being p produced
that's mass-produced that's no quality
not attractive. And yes, a lot of
devotional content that's out there that
says things that saints said that's not
true or have other things which are good
things at the end, good messages, go to
mass, etc. There's a lot of deep fakes
right now of the pope. a lot of deep
fakes from from that are inviting to do
good things and we have to be weary of
those things and also put a line cuz
even though they're inviting us to the
sacraments to do good things and they're
orthodox let's say
>> it's not the pope and then Jose what
what do you think are some of the
solutions for that because as the
technology gets better it'll be harder
and harder for someone who's not you
know doesn't have the tools to
completely verify how are they going to
be able to tell the difference I I know
that there were some you borderline
comical in some senses of, you know, the
Pope Francis with a big Gucci outfit,
you know. I mean, I think for most
people, they they knew pretty quickly
that it wasn't. But if we're looking at,
you know, um this video technology that
that's getting really good, um the photo
cameras and the the AI software, I mean,
it's going to be for I think for a lot
of people who don't have that much time
and there's so much content coming out,
where where can you hold on to? How can
you tell the difference? Well, it's as
has always been, you know, like go to
the sources, which is freaking difficult
for Catholics because yes, we want the
real. We got we want to highlight and we
we as like bore filters and not go
through the sources of our faith or of
what the pope is really saying not a
commentator or AI commentator in YouTube
and of course not a deep fake but so
difficult like we need formation around
this and we need and of course it's all
discernment but we're poorly formed as
Catholics in general right and then we
receive the videos that have good things
or that say good things apparently and
it's so easy to fall into a trap. But
it's all about discerning, right? So, we
will need to start doing a lot of things
in the church. And thankfully, Pope Leon
knows this. And we're going to get some
really cool surprises next year, the end
of this year, next surprises, next year
on on this this whole thing that a lot
of it is the same thing that we have
always thought is the answer, but we
have poorly done it. No formation.
And Matthew, how do you how do you see
using AI to help um you know confront
this this challenge of deep fakes and of
you know kind of this overwhelming
sensation of too much information?
>> Well, I mean let me start by
acknowledging I agree with everything
said uh I I I think there's obviously
there's opportunities and there's
significant challenges here. I mean I
mean one of the amazing opportunities I
think that AI is is kind of bringing to
the whole influencer uh space is I
probably some of us have seen how you
can like voice clone right in sync
right? So, if I if I we record this
podcast in English, effectively, I can
then like an AI can come in and and and
change my lips and my and and actually
have me speak Chinese, right? Which is
incredible, right? Because then I get to
reach people in Chinese. So, it's like
that's a really great example of how
kind of like a it's almost like a deep
fake technology, right? It's actually
put at our service. And so, when we when
we when it's useful, right, and and
we're choosing it because it serves
mission and it makes sense, AI can mean
incredible unlock for for for bringing
people the gospel, right? So, I I think
that's I'm really excited about that. Of
course, the deep fakes things is
obviously very troubling. We're all very
aware of I think why this could become a
major problem, right? Um the pope, even
a deep fake pope video made with the
right intentions, but being just a
little bit off doctrinal can cause
massive ripples around the world can
cause all kinds of issues. So, you know,
so I think there's there's two there's
two parts to this. One is I fully agree
the best way to mitigate the downside of
this is just ensure everyone's got solid
formation, right? I mean
>> so easy to get
>> somebody saw information they're going
be like that doesn't sound me right and
let me go check it out and and Madison's
like he never said that so now I know
but but uh I think that there also
there's a responsibility I think on the
platforms and things as well as as well
and I think this there's I think that
the church among governments and other
organizations should be lobbing the
platforms to say listen you guys
effectively are are very capable of
detecting when something is a deep fake
right so if somebody's uploading a piece
of content to your platform and you
detect that it's an it's an AI and that
and they're impersonating, right, a a
public figure, right? I mean, or really
anyone, right? Um, that's not cool. You
have I mean, in the very least, they
should have to label it, right? And say
and say say like very overtly that this
is AI generated content, right?
>> But you know what? For instance, the
deep fake. So, we we started creating a
list because well, listeners, etc. The
voice of the pope, that's one of the of
the channels in YouTube. If you see the
description at the end it says it's AI
generated but every thumbnail the pope
said whatever the pope gave this special
blessing and but it says at the end it
says so they label it but still
>> enough like totally I actually think
like and and hen does this for instance
right there's a watermark on every frame
like when the video starts you can see
right there like and I think this has to
be kind of a universal standard
>> that this is AI generated content and I
so I can't escape it and also this is
also the craziest
for audio too there has to be some kind
of watermark right where it has to
acknowledge this is AI generated content
and and this is difficult like to uh
it's difficult to roll out right because
there's lots of regulatory comp and it
provides a lot of cooperation between
the companies but actually I think in
the end you're going to find the
companies are first of all probably
going to welcome this in a lot of ways
because there's a lot of risk for them
as a platform right if they get involved
with spreading misinformation and things
like that they open themselves up to
litigation and things so I I think it
just requires like uh uh they have to
know that the governments are going to
be turning their guns and and if they
know that it's coming, I think what
you'll see is a lot of cooperation
amongst the companies to work on a
protocol like this. It just takes a
little nudge and I think actually the
pope ones in particular are particularly
big concern and I think if the the
church itself was to get involved in
saying hey listen like YouTube you got
to do something about this because you
know the OC is not cool with the defakes
and so we know you can do something so
please do. The thing is where where's
the line right cuz okay AI generated but
you know how YouTube has the categories
right entertainment or whatever and if
it's not news and it's entertainment you
can have even fake news right that like
that's a fact right
>> January that I was I spent I don't know
>> like half an hour uh Colonel Taglet he
was trying to
>> to ask me and and try to see how to see
he he said There's a lot of videos in
YouTube about me saying that I'm going
to be the next book that I made a pact
with Francis and stuff and he was so
like I've talked with everyone but they
can't do anything because it says at the
end like it entertainment not news so
they can say whatever and some deep
fakes some other stuff like there's no
line.
>> I mean I mean it's it's yeah it's
seriously like a deep concern right
because in the end of the day we don't
want necessarily a particular government
um determining what's real and what's l
>> or or company
>> or a company. Yeah. because obviously
they don't have a great track record,
right? So, and we all know that and so I
think and we should be deeply
uncomfortable with it. And so I I do
think right like I think that there's
there's severing degrees of of like
necessity here like I think one is which
I think is really obvious right is that
if if a piece of content is generated in
the voice with the image of a particular
person and it's not that person like
that person effectively should own their
own representation right you shouldn't
you they legally should have like some
kind of like copyright over their own
image and their own voice and if you use
that right without their permission that
should that should open you up to like
to possibly for litigation. Right? So
that's a very it's it's new grounds and
obviously that legal presence are are
going to be very sparse and obviously
it's complex. But I think from a common
sense perspective there isn't a person
alive like who would be comfortable with
people just taking their image and voice
and doing whatever they want they want
with it. Right? So I think I think like
from a grassroots perspective you'll
probably find that policy makers will
have a lot more success in fact act
enacting laws on this um because
there'll be such overwhelming grass
supports. And then the question is like
where do we go from there? Right? And I
think that that could be that could be
negotiated and and certainly it becomes
like reporting information that's
actually not true but but things that
you did. So they're not using your image
or your voice but they're reporting on
something you did which which is not
directly supported by evidence, right?
And so that that would be like an area
that we obviously we want to look at. Um
but that becomes a lot more challenging,
right? So I think we start with with the
whole personhood thing and the
sovereignty of the person and then we go
from there
>> and and even go like the Vatican with
Publio. I think we're going to start
having the Vatican push some some some
of this not just like the personal but
as an institution who well will be an
east part of the conversation as you
know well with you and and and so many
others but people inside the church the
Vatican will have to be very clear with
like there can't be anything from the
pope etc and the Vatican will have to
guide away somehow in so many different
>> way I think that's that's what I'm
excited about like especially the work
that you're doing and and the
opportunities we have here to work is
like there's a really an opportunity
here for the church to champion
something that is really important and
actually touches everybody in the world,
right? I mean, the pope fighting the
battle to ensure that people aren't deep
faking what he says, right? I mean, in
fact, what he's doing is he's
championing a cause which all of us
shout
and I I think that that's really
exciting and I think because he's a you
know, I mean, I think he's the greatest
like soft power in the world. He's the
most influential morph figure in the
world. I think there's a company alive
who wants to fight him on that. So, so I
think if he comes out and the Vatican
comes out and says, "Listen, this has
got to stop.
>> What they're going to have to
effectively do, right, uh, in order to
respect what he said can apply to
anyone, right? So, it really is going to
come down to it's it's I think there
will be tactical challenges, but really
this is going to come down to will. So,
how much should the companies the the
country care about moving on this?" And
I and I think when it comes down to what
the Pope wants and and and and you know
what what what hill the companies choose
choose to like die on, right? I just
don't think this is one they're going to
want to die on.
>> No. And then Jose, if I may, um, how do
you see the relationship between the the
local dascese, the bishops, uh, the
priests with the Catholic influencers as
influencers take a disproportionate
amount of, you know, amount of effect,
amount of influence for for lack of a
better word. You know, many of these
young people oftenimes they have
millions of followers and they they can
really sway the conversation. and they
can focus on their own, you know, what
they they see as a critical issue or a
priority and sometimes for for wonderful
effect and sometimes obviously, you
know, it can kind of become a very
negative cycle and and it can really
>> I love what you're talking about.
>> How how does that relationship how do
you see that changing and what are the
ways in which the the local priests, the
local bishops can really build a
constructive relationship with these
influencers? I I love that question
because
there's a lot of work behind the scenes
that has been happening these last
almost well like three years and a half
four years with the with with the
Vatican and and now that's sort of
rolling over to conferences of bishops
and even dascese we have some pilots
going on but first of all it's part of
the ordinary magistrum right of of of
the church the recognizing the online
because we we have to start there
recognizing the internet as the new
missionary frontier. It's a new
Europagus. It's where people are at
>> all day long where they're we're at.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. They're they're spending time.
Yes. There's vices there. But but
there's something they're looking for.
They're longing for purpose, for love,
for for the truth, for for God without
knowing it. So So who's there? leading
them to Christ, introducing to Christ
his love, his mercy, and walking with
them towards the fullness of the truth,
towards the the church, the sacraments.
Well, if a church institutionally
hasn't, and we're too late in the game,
well, there's a lot of lay people and
and priests and religious that have been
doing it some for a while, right, in
podcast, YouTube, and well, started with
blogs, you remember those, etc., etc.
and and now the the the church
recognizes they are missionaries in this
digital continent as Pope Benedict
coined it 2009 right and they're doing
the same thing that we were called to do
go and make disciples of every nation go
to the ends of the world that's what
they're doing so it's not a new thing
the same mission and what have we've
always been doing when we encounter a
new place a new culture because if you
see you ask a soci ologist. Yes, the
internet has the elements of of of a
culture. No, it's it own language,
customs, etc., etc. We found out a new
culture and we sent missionaries
and they weren't there. Of course, they
know the language initially. Savior went
there. He didn't preach in Spanish to
the Indians, right? To in India or Japan
or China or whatever. He had to learn
the language. But since the beginning,
he was a witness. And since the
beginning he was preaching, let's say
with his actions and and seeing the
seats of the verve in the local culture
and then knew the language engaged and
well presented them or introduce them to
to Christ. So the church recognized that
now people are at this new culture. It's
the new missionary frontier. And what
has the church always done? Warm them.
They didn't ah you want to go on a
mission? No. Of course they were formed.
They were accompanied. Of course, it was
letters and every so often they came
back in both and took whatever there was
letters going back and forth and they
were supported by the by the superior or
the bishop, right? The religious
superior. That's what we have done. And
of course, it's been like dangerous and
we know a lot of stories of martyrs
didn't come back because yes, difficult
culture, the pagan cultures in a lot of
ways and also a lot of them. Yeah, the
culture was too attractive and came
pagan, right? We don't know that many
stories, but there were a lot of them,
right? So, the internet's the whole
thing, but we need to form form the
digital missionaries going there,
accompany them, right? Well, send them
of course and support them. And that
those four things are now part of the
ordinary stream. So, that's happening.
Local like bishops are called to have an
encounter with their local official
missionaries. Ah but he lives in Dallas
and most of his followers are in New
York
we are like jurisdiction wise you live
this dascese this is your shepherd right
even though you have was the same thing
with books and he lost that here and yes
they were going to be sent somewhere
else to be sold doesn't matter you have
your own bishop so now bishops all over
the world and in the US starting
different ways but now we have pilots in
which they are meeting their their their
local Catholic creators, getting to know
them, ask them questions. Why are they
doing this? What are they doing? What's
what's in their heart? And then
accompany them. And yes, that sometimes
means a as you said, like no, you're
going this way, this way. Truth is
important for us. It has to be within
this bounds. Charity is also important.
Has to be this. We're trying to be one.
And then looks different with dascese.
That looks different. Sometimes this has
to it's a new thing. a digital ministry
office somewhere or under evangelization
or under the communications department.
The thing is the bishop our shepherds
are accomp recognizing them. They're
missionaries in the same mission and
accompany them while they do
evangelization and bring people not for
more followers and and to for people to
continue doom scrolling and just likes
or listens reviews but to bring it to
the church. So that's happening. It's
part of our magistream. A lot of
conferences are working on it. Some
dasces are very open already piloting
all over the world and and that's I
don't know that's very exciting. It's a
new missionary chapter in the church.
>> That is very exciting. And um and
Matthew as you know AI and emerging tech
continues to be more and more integrated
into um into the local churches and into
the universal church. Where do you see
opportunity to you know help these
influencers get their message better
across use AI and help the local dascese
also use AI so that when you know people
are intellectually converted they are
able to find a home they're able to find
a parish that can suit their needs.
Yeah, I mean it's it's a big question. I
mean I think there are platforms that
are struggling with this this issue of
what we call off-ramping, right? Which
is um when users uh stumble across our
platform. It could be because they
watched a podcast and they heard some
idea mentioned and they wanted to look
into the idea or ask questions about it
and so they they come across Magisteri,
right? Or they end up on the hollow app
and uh in the process of asking
questions and getting answers that
sometimes they may uh effectively be
intellectually converted, right? But
then they they need to take the next
step. So then the question is where do
we offer them to right? I think there's
a still this is still a very important
area where we need to kind of figure out
what that kind of pipeline kind of looks
like. I mean we send them directly to
the parish or we send them to kind of a
middleware platform that help them find
community or
>> both or do both. Yeah. And I I think
like there's a real opportunity for the
lady like I and I think it's it's really
important that the ladies step up and
recognize that figuring this out uh is
something that we have to do. Like we
have to lead on this and and for no
other reason our pastors are are busier
than they've ever been before. uh it's
not necessarily their their their domain
of expertise uh like technology and the
new media and so as much as possible we
have to step up and say how how can we
how can we lead on this how can we
demonstrate and run pilots and
demonstrate the effectiveness of it uh
and and also just acknowledge that um
and we were talking about this earlier I
mean God is is calling not just priests
to serve and preach the gospel but
ladies so it's also effectively have the
humility to recognize that God may have
imbue a certain gift and he may be
calling us to serve and then so in
finding ways to nurture nurture that
vocation and I think a lot of this comes
down into I think you know leadership at
at the dascese and I think you know too
often I think we take and I used to I'm
speaking for someone who used to work
for an arch dascese in a chancery right
too often in the arch dasis we can think
of ourselves as more like the
inquisition right and not enough as
shepherds right so everyone my my you
know my pastoral responsibilities you
know doing confirmations uh or dating or
dating priests and so on and then
effectively most of my time is on saying
you can do this but you can't do that
right but obviously the pastor role
extends well beyond that and ultimately
like a shepherd who's is is going to be
effective in role has to be one with the
sheep feel deeply that the shepherd
cares for their interests and he will be
willing to risk his own life right and
poorest poorest his heart and soul then
to ensure that their their souls are
safeguarded and I just want to say like
I want to echo what Jose said because I
think it's it's probably the most
important point here is like
relationship is is I I really believe
that when someone is is possibly called
within the dascese to be a lay a lay
missionary a lay influencer that that
that has to be that call has to be
validated of course and verified If that
call is there, then then it's important
for the local priest and for the bishop
to develop a deep and meaningful
relationship which is which is really
based upon care and concern and love for
that person because if they if they feel
that um that my priest or my bishop is
reaching out because they love me and
they want to support me in my ministry
and and they they feel that there's
there's something that God has called me
to and I'm effectively doing it. Well,
then they know that the influence feels
that they have their back. they're gonna
be much they're gonna be much more open,
right, to say to to you saying, "Hey, by
the way, I watched your last podcast.
You may want to consider emphasizing
this, right? And you know this because I
love you and I and I support your
mission." Not not because you know you
you said something you're not supposed
to. It's my job to step and say,
"Nuhuh." Like like that's right. That's
right. So I I I I think if and I know
this is difficult because again bishops
are as busy, priests are as busy as ever
have been before. But I but I do think
amongst I'm speaking as a lay person
when there's a lay person in our dascese
who have calling I am totally cool like
like with with getting a little less
facetime with the bishop or my priest to
ensure that that that vocation is is is
respectively nurtured because I know
that person will reach far more
effectively people and because I care
about winning souls for Christ as like
anybody else that person succeeding will
mean more souls and and I'm so I think
that that that's a tension but I think
that that's ultimately that the lay
people have to rally around support
their bishops and priests in in this
particular their outreach.
>> And Jose, in the final moments here of
the podcast, because we're we're mindful
that you have to go. Um you're here in
Rome uh as part of the Jubilee and the
digital missionaries, what's um what's
something that stood out to you here
during this visit or something that
you've learned that you're you're
excited to take back home to Dallas and
and work on with your with the network?
O so many things but um I think um like
a new thing a a lot of things but but
mostly we've been doing this um trying
working with influencers from all over
the world um and then before the the
Senate and then doing different things
here in Rome and the Vatican. One of the
things that's the best thing that
happened even through Zoom um seeing
that they're not alone. know seeing the
faces like the testimonies of these
people like oh I thought I was alone and
now I see there's a lot of other people
doing it but well I sort of knew that I
I I knew but but I don't feel alone
because I saw the pope call me digital
missionary and talk like when when he
appeared on Tuesday Tuesday Tuesday the
last Tuesday of July right and and gave
these cool remarks I saw the secretary
of state talking. I saw the prop prefect
of the datastry of evangelization. I saw
the prefect of the communications
psychiatry. I saw all these people that
are like they're in the Vatican that
seems so far away and they talked about
traditional missionaries and they say
that the church wants to like sees us
recognize what we're doing. That changed
everything. And we have a lot of
testimonies these last several years of
people who were like, "Yeah, I'm done."
And when we started having these zooms
with people here and then having these
special like sending um sending I don't
know how you call them like ceremonies
or whatever in Zoom that you're being
sent online to evangelize and bring
people to the truth everything starts
changing because we're called to be one
and yes we're apostolic right successors
of the apostles like it's a thing we're
Catholic 100% Catholic so for for
everyone now going back to their places
and seeing the church saw me and now I
also can go and I feel can go and knock
the the door at my my bishops
well the communication direct
evangelization whatever in the dascese
and start walking with men and well tell
them out everything that things that are
coming for for evangelization because
yeah pastoral everything but also like
evangelization that's what we need to be
doing totally where people are at right
>> and it's risky of course there's a lot
of risk with being online and yes it's
not like even a nikilops that open book
like recognizing it's not like okay
you're a valid certificate influence
Catholic influence approved doesn't mean
that right like now you blank to do
whatever but you're a missionary you're
being accompanied by the church that
seeing that in the faces of people from
all over proof that changes everything
new missionary impulse going back
>> beautiful and on that note Jose thank
you so much for the incredible work that
you're doing Matthew, Jose, it's been a
a real pleasure to speak with both of
you today. Thank you for having me.
Thank you.